Guide to the Harold D. Gunn Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Harold D. Gunn collection
1908-1982
MS 1586
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
11.75
The papers include a unique collection of reports, memoranda, maps and anthropological and historical notes generated by officials and researchers who worked for the British colonial administration in Northern Nigeria. The materials document aspects of the policy of Indirect Rule pursued by the Colonial Government dating ca. 1908-1950, including the establishment and consolidation of a hierarchy of administrative units for ruling rural Nigerians. A good number of the files were produced in the years 1925-1940 when the application of Indirect Rule was intensified. The files were meant to provide subsequent Colonial officers with an "official knowledge" of the culture, language, economic activities, beliefs and other customs of each locality and ethnic group. Individuals who authored several of these files include J. H. Shaw, C. K. Meek, J. G. Davies, F. G. Raynolds, D. A. Percival, C. W. Rowlings, and R. C. S. Stanley. The collection also includes Harold Gunn's correspondence and research notes from 1931 to 1982.
Gunn, H. D.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Virginia Gunn, 1990 and 1993-1996.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in six series: I. Provincial Files, ca. 1908-1951. II. Ethnic Groups, 1921-1967. III. Topical Files, 1913-1950. IV. Northern Nigerian Languages, 1921-1968. V. Harold Gunn Personal Papers, 1931-1982. VI. Administrative Maps and Sketches, 1913-1948.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of a unique collection of reports, memoranda, research materials and maps that document aspects of the policy of Indirect Rule pursued by the British Colonial Government of Nigeria dating ca. 1908-1950. The focus includes the ways the Colonial Government subsequently implemented this policy by establishing and consolidating a hierarchy of new administrative units. The information on this process was compiled by two groups of government functionaries who performed largely complimentary duties. The first group consisted of district officers who served as frontline implementors of the colonial project. The other group involved experts, mainly research anthropologists, who were charged with the tasks of "understanding" and "documenting" the cultures, languages and administrative customs of the "natives."
Reports compiled by district officers can be broadly categorized into two types. A considerable number of them describe specific administrative duties at a district level and were part of a larger collection called "District Notebooks." These files seek to "assess" and sometimes "reassess" the process of "organizing" and "reorganizing" different areas into a three-tier vertically connected administrative structure. These three levels were, in a descending order, provinces, divisions, and districts. For the most part, Northern Nigeria was divided into eleven provinces, namely, Adamawa, Bauchi, Benue, Bornu, Ilorin, Kabba, Kano, Niger, Plateau, Sokoto and Zaria. Each province was further divided into divisions, and each division into several districts. All villages and localities of Nigeria were gradually incorporated into this framework, except a few districts which were recognized as "independent districts," sometimes called "emirates," to be governed by hereditary rulers.
The most rare items in this collection include place name gazetteers for almost all the eleven provinces. Produced with official authorization of the British, these gazetteers were used, among other things, for generating a number of maps illuminating administrative boundaries, settlement patterns, landscapes and road networks (see series VI below).
Other scarce items in the collection include district-specific files entitled "Intelligence Reports" produced by prominent colonial officers including J. H. Shaw, C. K. Meek, J. G. Davies, F. G. Raynolds, D. A. Percival, C. W. Rowlings, and R. C. S. Stanley. These reports provide original information on wide-ranging administrative and political issues that the indirect rule policy encountered upon implementation. Some of these issues included public disturbance, inter-district border disputes, inter-ethnic conflicts, problems of succession among customary rulers of different "tribes," and resistance to taxes and government attempts at restricting population movement and power of native courts. Some of the reports also document government concerns with witchcraft, magic and aspects of "traditional" marriage customs, such as "concubinage," dowry and "marriage by exchange." Harold D. Gunn and his fellow anthropologists at the International African Studies Institute used some of this information in writing materials for a series called "Ethnography of Africa South of the Sahara."
The collection also includes a large number of memoranda through which senior officials at provincial capitals communicated with their subordinates at divisional and district levels. On their turn, lower officials kept their superiors informed by sending back a number of reports and letters. Most of these correspondence files are dated, signed and sealed. Researchers would find them useful for reconstructing administrative and political histories of the region. Finally, researchers would also find a large collection of vocabularies and research materials on more than forty Northern Nigerian local languages.
Biographical / Historical
Harold Dale Gunn was born in Dallas, Texas, on August 3, 1918. He received a B.A from Southern Methodist University in 1941 and an M.A. from the University of London in 1949. From 1949 to 1952, Gunn was a research anthropologist for the International African Institute (IAI) in Nigeria. He taught anthropology at the University of Connecticut from 1952 to 1957. In 1960, Gunn became the curator of the African Collections at Lincoln University in Pennsylvania, and also taught sociology and anthropology. He was head of the Department of Sociology, Anthropology and Human Services at Lincoln University from 1975 to 1979. Gunn died in 1989.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Ethnology -- Nigeria, Northern; Fula (African people); Hausa (African people); Tiv (African people); Tuaregs -- Nigeria; Wolof (African people); Adamawa Province (Nigeria); Bauchi Province (Nigeria); Benue Province (Nigeria); Bornu Province (Nigeria); Ilorin Province (Nigeria); Kabba Province (Nigeria); Kano Province (Nigeria); Niger Province (Nigeria); Nigeria, Northern -- Gazetteers; Nigeria, Northern -- Administrative and political divisions -- Maps; Nigeria, Northern -- Administrative and political divisions; Nigeria, Northern -- Colonial influence; Nigeria, Northern -- History; Nigeria, Northern -- Languages; Nigeria, Northern; Plateau Province (Nigeria); Sokoto Province (Nigeria); Zaria Province (Nigeria); Gunn, H. D.; Meek, C. K. (Charles Kingsley), 1885-1965
- Provincial Files, 1908-1951, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The British Colonial government of Northern Nigeria ruled this region by reorganizing it into three vertically connected administrative levels. These were, in a descending order, provinces, divisions, and districts. For the most part, the region was divided into eleven provinces, namely, Adamawa, Bauchi, Benue, Bornu, Ilorin, Kabba, Kano, Niger, Plateau, Sokoto and Zaria. Each province was further divided into divisions, and each division into several districts. All villages and localities of Northern Nigeria were incorporated into this structure except a few "independent districts" which were recognized as "emirates" and "chiefdoms" of co-opted hereditary rulers. Files in this series consist of memoranda, reports, and anthropological and historical notes produced by agents of the Colonial government who performed wide-ranging duties in different levels of this hierarchy. For this reason, the files are arranged both hierarchically and alphabetically. The series begins with folders of regional files that deal with different administrative issues pertaining to more than one province. This is followed by several files on eleven alphabetically arranged provinces and their subdivision districts.
  Files on each province are alphabetically arranged by administrative levels in a descending order. Researchers would first find "general files" that deal with issues pertaining to the province-level government or more than one of its constituent divisions. This is followed by files belonging to individual divisions of that province. The last sub-category consists of files that pertain to several other districts of the province for which we lack information on the division to which they belonged. As noted above, "emirates" were exceptions in legal status and autonomy. Nevertheless, each emirate was situated within the territory of one of the eleven provinces. For this reason, files pertaining to emirates are alphabetically listed with divisional-level files.
  - Regional: Northern Nigeria and West Africa
    - Administrative reorganization of primitive people [memo], undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Disturbance in northern provinces (Sierra Leone protectorate), memo from the Secretary of northern provinces, 1931 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Certificate given to Kaleri Tin Mines, Ltd., 1908 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Circular from the secretary of northern provinces on proposal to publish an anthropological sketch of the northern provinces, 1921 April 9 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - District notebooks [guideline to district officers for improving standard of notebooks], undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Investigation outstanding [regarding pagan administrative reorganization], undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Milk products legislation, 1950 February 8 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Native authorities, northern provinces appointed under section 3 (1) of native courts ordinance, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Nigerian arts and industries [memo from the secretary of northern provinces], 1931 January 20 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Nigerian craft industries, policy and instructions, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Northern Nigeria [questionnaires and notes on Benue, Niger, Plateau and Sokoto provinces], undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Pagan administration, notes for the guidance of officers engaged in inquiries connected with, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - A preliminary survey of pottery in West Africa [by M. A. Cardew, Department of Commerce and Industry, Lagos], 1950 July 31 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Report on French Equatorial and West Africa [by British Consulate General, Belgian Congo], 1936 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Study of economics, a guide for studying African economies, 1944 June 19 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Adamawa Province
    - General
      - Longuda tribe, anthropological notes on, 1929 May 29 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Notes on Adamawa, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Report on the Chubanawa, Madagali, Mubi and Ub-a districts of Adamawa province, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Muri Division
      - Bakundi district
        - Administrative report [by R. C. S. Stanley], 1933 (Box 2, Folder 19)
        - District head, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 20)
        - The Dirrim of Kwagiri and Baki [from Bakundi district notebook section on village administration], undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
        - Notes on personnel [by district head], 1933 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Dakka district, administrative report [by R. C. S. Stanley], undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Mumuye district
        - Extract from a letter from Mr. Meek, 1927 June 16 (Box 2, Folder 24)
        - Intelligence report on Mumuye and Zinna districts [by J. H. Shaw], undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
        - Mumuye assessment report [by T. H. Haughton], 1912 oct (Box 2, Folder 26)
        - The Mumuye tribe, report on [by J. H. Shaw], 1948 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Uba district
        - The Marg[h]i of Adamawa, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
        - The Uba pagan communities, Marghi tribe [by S. H. P. Vereker], 1942 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Verre district
        - Alantika -notes on [by A. A. Cullen], 1942 (Box 2, Folder 30)
        - Ethnological notes on the hill tribes [by T. A. G. Budgen], 1929 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Wase district, proposed transfer of, 1941 March 1 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Wurkum district
        - Ethnographic, historical, etc.: Excerpts from Wurkum district, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 33)
        - Ethnographic notes on the Wurkum, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
        - Wurkum tribe, notes and excerpts, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - Yungur district
        - Intelligence report on [by D. F. H. Macbridge], 1936 (Box 2, Folder 36)
        - The Yungur-speaking peoples, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - Zinna district, policy as to the status of [by Sergeant R. B. B. Eustace], undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - Zummo district, amalgamation of Zummo and Wafango districts, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Yola Emirate
      - Communication from T. F. Carlyle [district officer] to the Resident of Yola Emirate, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - Historical notes, etc. on Bashima, Batta and Bula pagans, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Other districts
      - Alkali district, "soke" précis of replies to the provincial secretary's memorandum, 1927 August 17 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Chamba (also called Bachama, Bachamba, Cham, Chubunawa) district
        - The Bachama, undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
        - Cham tribe- anthropological notes on, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 44)
        - Chamba, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
        - The Chamba tribe, report on [by J. Hunter Shaw], 1937 February 27 (Box 3, Folder 46)
        - Chamba-- ethnical and historical notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
        - The Chamba, etc.: on origin and organization [by D. A. Percival], 1938 January (Box 3, Folder 48)
        - Correspondence on and extracts from appendices to report on the Chamba tribe [by J. Hunter Shaw], 1936-1937 (Box 3, Folder 49)
        - Notes on the Bare [by C. K. Meek], 1928 (Box 3, Folder 50)
        - A Summary proposal for the combined Chubunawa/Madagali district, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 51)
        - The Tsugu (gasube) Chieftainate, extracts from appendices to Shaw's Chamba reorganization report, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 52)
      - Gashaka district
        - History of Gashaka from Fulani times [for the district notebook by W. H. Paul], 1939 (Box 3, Folder 53)
        - Mambila Tribes, Gashaka district [extracts from a report by Captain T.A. Izard], 1926 (Box 3, Folder 54)
        - Summary of proposal [Gashaka district reorganization], undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Kentu district, notes and abstracts of materials in various reports on organization of Kentu district, 1934-1949 (Box 3, Folder 56)
      - Kilba district, the Kilba, undated (Box 3, Folder 57)
      - Kona district, notes and excerpts from report by J. E. Davies, 1933-1936 (Box 3, Folder 58)
      - Mambila district
        - Intelligence report on the Mambila area, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 59)
        - Mambila tribe, ethnological report [by C. K. Meek], 1929 (Box 3, Folder 60)
        - Village list with population and livestock figures and tax rates, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 61)
      - Mboi district, Mboi, undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
      - Mbula ("Bulla") district
        - The Mbula, undated (Box 3, Folder 63)
        - Report on ["M"] Bulla reassessment [by Ryan], 1913 (Box 3, Folder 64)
      - Mubi district
        - Intelligence report on [by J. H. Shaw], undated (Box 3, Folder 65)
        - Village heads [report by J. E. Davies], undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Bauchi Province
    - General
      - Ethnographic notes on various tribes in Bauchi, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 67)
      - Minutes by His Excellency the governor, 1920 May 21 (Box 4, Folder 68)
      - Organization of pagan administration in Sayawa tribe, 1934 May 5 (Box 4, Folder 69)
      - Selection of notes from Bauchi, 1950 August 2 (Box 4, Folder 70)
      - Suggestions as to making a separate province of Bauchi, 1910-1920 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Gombe Division (also referred to as "Emirate")
      - Assessment of Gombe town, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 72)
      - Gombe Emirate, undated (Box 4, Folder 73)
      - Kanam district
        - Assessment report on Kanam district [by F. Edgar], 1914 (Box 4, Folder 74)
        - Burrum of Kanam [report by O. H. Best], 1926 March 22 (Box 4, Folder 75)
        - Jarawa tribe, undated (Box 4, Folder 76)
        - The Jarawa group (see also pagan peoples of the Plateau Province), undated (Box 4, Folder 77)
        - The hill Jarawa [by A. T. Clark], 1950 (Box 4, Folder 78)
        - Kenam -Wase boundary, 1931 April 14 (Box 4, Folder 79)
        - Sources- the Jarawa group, undated (Box 4, Folder 80)
      - Lemma district
        - A few notes on tribes in Lemma district, undated (Box 4, Folder 81)
        - Report on Rahaman village area in Lemma district, undated (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Missau Emirate, explanation of our modes of livelihood and occupations [from Sarakin Missau Ahmadu], 1944 March 4 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Other districts
      - Ningi district, the administration of the pagans of Ningi by G. H. Payton, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 84)
      - Tangale-Waja district
        - Administration of Waja district, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 85)
        - Dadiya native authority, progress report, 1937 March 28 (Box 4, Folder 86)
        - East Tangale district, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 87)
        - Erosion and reforestation schemes Tangale-Waja Biliri resettlement scheme, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 88)
        - Filiya, report on Filiya resettlement, 1948 October 24 (Box 4, Folder 89)
        - Pagan administration, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 90)
        - Reorganization progress report [Waja district], 1948 June 10 (Box 4, Folder 91)
        - Report on the Tangale-Waja districts [by A. B. Mathews], 1934 (Box 4, Folder 92)
        - Report on Waja district [by S. W. Walker], 1929 (Box 4, Folder 93)
        - Résumé of and comments on A. B. Mathews's suggestions for the reorganization of Tangale Waja districts, undated (Box 4, Folder 94)
        - Tangale-Waja native administration, undated (Box 4, Folder 95)
        - Waja tribe, anthropological notes on, 1929 May 4 (Box 4, Folder 96)
        - Waja assessment report, 1928 February 13 (Box 4, Folder 97)
      - Yemaltu (also called "Tera") district
        - Belewa tribe, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 98)
        - The Jukon town of Pindiga, extract from ethnographic notes on the Belewa [by R. C. Abraham], 1930 (Box 4, Folder 99)
        - Report on the proposed reorganization of Yamaltu (Tera) district [by H. D. Murray], 1948 (Box 4, Folder 100)
        - Tara notebooks [by W. M. Wood], undated (Box 4, Folder 101)
  - Benue Province
    - General
      - Benue-Adamawa provincial boundary, notes and excerpts, 1943-1948 (Box 5, Folder 102)
      - Boundary between northern and southern provinces, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 103)
      - Insuleke, chineke or dancing women, 1925-1926 (Box 5, Folder 104)
      - Miscellaneous notes and reports on Benue, undated (Box 5, Folder 105)
      - Notes and abstracts [on Benue], undated (Box 5, Folder 106)
      - Plateau, undated (Box 5, Folder 107)
      - Provincial indicators, undated (Box 5, Folder 108)
      - Some Munshi songs, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 109)
      - Teshena tribe, anthropological notes on, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 110)
    - Idoma division
      - Clan headship of Ito, 1949 September 15 (Box 6, Folder 111)
      - Dance guilds, 1936 December 7 (Box 6, Folder 112)
      - Disturbance in Ito, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 113)
      - Ethnographic notes on tribes in Idoma, undated (Box 6, Folder 114)
      - Ibo immigration into Idoma, undated (Box 6, Folder 115)
      - Intelligence report, the clans of Ai-Onu, Ai-Odu and Ai-Ochagbaha, undated (Box 6, Folder 116)
      - Intelligence report, the clans of Okwoga, Ebiyi, Ichama, Edumoga and Obokolo, undated (Box 6, Folder 117)
      - Notes and maps on Kamantan, Agatu, Egedde, Igala, etc., undated (Box 6, Folder 118)
      - Worku status, undated (Box 6, Folder 119)
    - Katagun division
      - Notes, from Katagun divisional office (Azare), 1951 (Box 6, Folder 120)
      - Touring report on Azare and Galadima districts (of Katagun division), 1950 June 14 (Box 6, Folder 121)
    - Keffi Emirate
      - Administrative reorganization of Karshi district, preliminary report, 1935 April 23 (Box 6, Folder 122)
      - Ethnological notes on Kwottos of Toto (Panda) district [by Captain J. R. Wilson-Haffenden], undated (Box 6, Folder 123)
      - Index to notes on Gwari, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 124)
      - Intelligence report on the tribes inhabiting the Karu district of Keffi Emirate [by M. H. Varvill], undated (Box 6, Folder 125)
      - Karshi district
        - Intelligence report, Karshi district [by M. H. Varvill], 1937 May 10 (Box 6, Folder 126)
        - Organization of Karshi district [by A. G. C. Stainforts], 1935 May 5 (Box 6, Folder 127)
      - Yeskwas (also called "Yesakawa") district
        - Intelligence report on Yeskwas district [by M. H. Varvill], 1936 February 26 (Box 6, Folder 128)
        - Reassessment of Yeskwas district [report by W. Laurence Cox], 1933 August 9 (Box 6, Folder 129)
        - Reorganization of Yeskwas tribe, undated (Box 6, Folder 130)
        - Some notes on Yeskwas in the Yeskwas district of Keffi Emirate, undated (Box 6, Folder 131)
    - Lafia Emirate
      - The Mi Gili (Koro) tribe of Lafia, undated (Box 6, Folder 132)
      - Native administration, undated (Box 6, Folder 133)
      - Reassessment report [by W. S. E. Warren, with Resident's covering notes], 1933 (Box 6, Folder 134)
      - Reassessment report on Lafia Emirate Tiv [by R. E. Alford, see also Tiv Province], undated (Box 6, Folder 135)
      - Reorganization of Lafia Emirate [by W. S. E. Warren, with marginal notes by the Resident of Benue], undated (Box 6, Folder 136)
      - Report on the Tiv of the Harev/Tiondo clan in the Keana district of the Lafia Emirate [by W. S. Warren, see also Tiv division], undated (Box 6, Folder 137)
    - Nasarawa Emirate
      - The Afu tribe of Nasarawa, undated (Box 6, Folder 138)
      - The Gwargwada district of Nasarawa, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 139)
      - Intelligence report on the tribes inhabiting the Gwargwada district [by T. E. Letchworth], 1936 July 14 (Box 6, Folder 140)
      - Report on the village and district administration of Umaisha Toto and Gwargwada districts, undated (Box 6, Folder 141)
    - Tiv division
      - Abinsi town, administration of [by K. P. Muddocks], undated (Box 7, Folder 142)
      - Administration of Tiv division [by paramount chief and council], 1946-1947 (Box 7, Folder 143)
      - Bette-Bendi clan, extracts from anthropological report on the Bette-Bendi clan of which the Egedde are said to be a sub-clan [by A. F. R. Stoddart], 1932 (Box 7, Folder 144)
      - Dispositions of witnesses in a trial for murder in the magistrate's court of the Jos magisterial district, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 145)
      - Gav district, reorganization of, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 146)
        - Idoma -Tiv boundary, 1939 July 7 (Box 7, Folder 147)
        - Intelligence report on the Riverain Jukun of Tiv division, undated (Box 7, Folder 148)
        - Intelligence report on the Tongov clan of the Tiv tribe [by I. G. Gunn], 1934 (Box 7, Folder 149)
        - Ipav clan, intelligence report on [by K. P. Maddocks], 1937 (Box 7, Folder 150)
        - Katsina ala town, intelligence report [by K. P. Maddocks], 1935 December 30 (Box 7, Folder 151)
        - Katsina ala area, report on organization of, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 152)
      - Kunav district
        - Kunav, organization, undated (Box 7, Folder 153)
        - Reorganization report, Kunav north district [by R. F. Alford], 1935 (Box 7, Folder 154)
      - Mbakor district